Register of the Arnold Ellsworth True papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Arnold Ellsworth True papers
1885-1990
90011
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (7.2 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings relating to American naval operations in the Pacific Theater during World War II, especially the sinking of the destroyer Hammann at the battle of Midway, anti-war protest movements in the United States during the Vietnam War, and government surveillance of these movements. Includes United States government documents released under the Freedom of Information Act.
True, Arnold Ellsworth, 1901-1979.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1901 Born, Owen County, Kentucky
1920 Graduate, United States Naval Academy; commissioned ensign, U.S. Navy
1931 M.S. in meteorology, Massachusetts Institute of Technology
1939 Graduate, U.S. Naval War College
1939-1942 Commanding officer, U.S.S. Hammann
1942-1943 Commanding officer, Destroyer Division Three
1943-1944 Commanding officer, Destroyer Squadron Two
1945-1946 Staff officer, Atlantic Fleet
1946 Retired from U.S. Navy as rear admiral
1947-1968 Professor of meteorology, San Jose State College
1969 Member, U.S. Study Team on Religious and Political Freedom in Vietnam
1979 Died, Palo Alto, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The Arnold Ellsworth True papers document the life of a United States naval officer whose career took an unusual turn. The most dramatic moments of True's naval service came during World War II in 1942 when he was at the Battle of the Coral Sea and subsequently at the Battle of Midway as captain of the destroyer Hammann. At the Coral Sea, the Hammann came to the relief of the stricken aircraft carrier Lexington and was credited with saving hundreds of American seamen from the sinking ship. A somewhat similar situation arose at Midway when the Hammann came to the aid of the Yorktown. While efforts to contain damage on the crippled carrier were underway it was hit by more torpedoes, and so too was the Hammann as it lay alongside. Both ships were lost. Many of the Hammann's crew died, and True himself was wounded. He was awarded the Navy Cross and the Distinguished Service Medal for his conduct in these battles.
After early disability retirement from the Navy, Admiral True undertook a second career as a faculty member at San Jose State College. Meanwhile, he had become increasingly convinced of the futility of war and became a Quaker, joining the Society of Friends in 1947. The bulk of the collection documents his advocacy of the cause of peace, especially during the Vietnam War era. True was an early opponent of American military involvement in Vietnam, and he successfully contested an effort by the U.S. Navy to prevent him, as a retired officer, from speaking out publicly on foreign policy issues. After the Navy withdrew its objections, in 1967 True embarked on a national speaking tour sponsored by Veterans for Peace in Vietnam. Together with a few other like-minded retired generals and admirals, among them retired Marine Corps General David M. Shoup, whose papers are also in the Hoover Institution Archives, he achieved national notice. Senator J. William Fulbright consulted him in conjunction with the Senate Foreign Relations Committee's investigation of the Tonkin Gulf incident. In 1969, Admiral True joined a study team mission to South Vietnam sponsored by American religious groups. The team produced a report critical of the U.S.-supported government of that country.
Also included in the collection are redacted official documents sought and received from U.S. government agencies by Corinne True, the admiral's widow, under the Freedom of Information Act. They document government surveillance of him and establish that he was a target of the Federal Bureau of Investigation's Counterintelligence Program (COINTELPRO).
Hammann (Ship); United States. Navy--Officers.; Internal security--United States.; Midway, Battle of, 1942.; Peace.; Radicalism--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Protest movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.
- Biographical File, 1901-1984 (Boxes 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal documents, biographical data, and printed matter relating to Arnold Ellsworth True.
  - Biographical data, 1901-1973 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Birth certificate and biographical sketches.
  - Obituaries, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Memorial service notes, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Biography, Arnold Ellsworth True: Destroyer Captain, Maverick Admiral, by Norman W. Shaw, 1980 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Drafts, finished typescript, and printed copy.
  - Family, 1941-1974 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Clippings and miscellany relating to family members.
  - General, 1925-1984
    Clippings, printed articles, certificates, notes, schedules, and miscellany relating to True or referring to him. Includes announcements and programs of events at which he was a speaker or which he attended.
    - 1925-1947 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1952-1958 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1961-1966 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - 1967 February-September (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1967 October-November (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1967 December (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1968 January-February (Box-folder 2: 2)
      Includes U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee hearings on Gulf of Tonkin incident.
    - 1968 March-May (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - 1968 June-October (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1969 January-June (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - 1969 July-December (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 3: 6)
      Includes World Citizens Assembly proceedings.
    - 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 3: 9)
      Posthumous references.
    - Undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Chronological File, 1932-1987 (Boxes 3-4)
  Compilation of photocopies of significant letters, writings, other documents, clippings, and photographs from the papers of Arnold Ellsworth True, arranged chronologically.
  - Bound copies, 1932-1967 (Box-folder 3: 11-12)
  - Expanded unbound copy, 1932-1987 (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
- United States Navy File, 1938-1976 (Box 4)
  Citations, awards, correspondence, and miscellany documenting the active duty U.S. Navy service of Arnold Ellsworth True and his official dealings with the Navy after retirement. See also: Declassified U.S. Government Records.
  - Citations and awards, 1938-1946 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    Includes U.S. Naval Academy Bachelor of Science certificate; Navy Cross, Distinguished Service Medal, Commendation Ribbon, and Bronze Star awards; and certificate of retirement.
  - Active duty correspondence, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Official correspondence and personnel records.
  - Correspondence with families of shipmates killed in action, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Miscellany, 1939-1945 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    Includes ship's newspapers, humorous writings, and histories of U.S.S. Morris and U.S.S. Mustin, ships under True's command.
  - Retirement correspondence, 1952-1976 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Official correspondence with the Department of the Navy. Unofficial correspondence with naval acquaintances can be found in the Correspondence series.
  - Speech ban controversy, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    Correspondence, memorandum, Department of Defense directives, and clippings relating to Department of the Navy effort to prevent True from speaking on foreign policy issues.
- San Jose State College File, 1953-1968 (Box 5)
  Correspondence, memoranda, and miscellany documenting the San Jose State College service of Arnold Ellsworth True.
  - Correspondence, 1953-1976 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Official college correspondence. Unofficial correspondence with colleagues can be found in the Correspondence series.
  - Meteorology program curricula for Bachelor of Science and Master of Science degrees, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Professors on the Right controversy, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    Memoranda and clippings relating to an academic freedom issue dispute with self-described Professors on the Right on the college campus.
  - Retirement notice and service award, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Miscellany, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    College publications and speech.
- Speeches and Writings, 1932-1979 (Boxes 5-8)
  Speeches and writings by Arnold Ellsworth True.
  - "The Structure of Tropical Cyclones," U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 1937 March (Box-folder 5: 6)
    Printed Spanish translation in Boletín del Observatorio Nacional (Cuba).
  - "The Other War," Common Sense, 1943 May (Box-folder 5: 7)
    Printed and typed copies. Published under pseudonym Commander.
  - "The Weather Man Sets D-Day," speech, Engineers' Club, San Francisco, California, 1944 May 11 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    Typescript.
  - "A Mathematical Interpretation of a Theory of the Universe,", 1944 November (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Speech to graduating class, U.S. Navy Technical School, Treasure Island, California, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - "Ends and Means: A Meditation,", circa 1946 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - "A Working Hypothesis,", 1946 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - "Statement on Universal Military Training,", 1951 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - "The Junto Club," speech to graduating class, U.S. Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey, California, 1953 January 23 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - "New Frontiers," speech to graduating class, Monterey Peninsula College, 1953 June 13 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    Typescript and mimeograph.
  - "World Peace," speech to graduating class, Pescadero Union High School, 1957 June 6 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - "The Wisdom of Insecurity," speech to graduating class, Pescadero Union High School, 1961 June 15 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    Mimeograph.
  - "Secret Dispatches of a Russian Diplomat" (satirical essay), 1962 February 21 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Perspective television program on meteorology (San Jose State College television series), 1963 April 20-27 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    Mimeographed transcripts.
  - "Economic Effects of Disarmament,", 1965 March (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - "Who's Gullible?,", 1965 May (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - "Vietnam," speech, San Jose, California, 1965 October 16 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - "Manipulation,", 1965 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - "The Tonkin Gulf Incident, August 2, 1964,", 1966 March (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - "Statement on Asian Policy and the Vietnam War,", 1966 April 18 (Box-folder 5: 25)
    Mimeograph and printed copy (U.S. Farm News, 1967 June).
  - "Washington Visitation, April 18-30, 1966,", circa 1966 April (Box-folder 5: 26)
    Mimeograph. Account of American Friends Service Committee meeting with Congressmen in Washington, D.C.
  - "Vietnam: Voices and Actions of Our Community,", 1966 December (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - "If the Vietnam War Escalates into China: The Military Problems, Risks and Prospects" (contribution to symposium), Minority of One, 1967 January (Box-folder 5: 28)
    Typescript and printed copy.
  - Speech, Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace national meeting, Washington, D.C., 1967 September 27 (Box-folder 5: 29)
    Printed copy.
  - "Can We Win in Vietnam? Veterans Stars and Stripes for Peace,", 1967 October (Box-folder 5: 30)
    Typescript, printed copy, and U.S. Farm News reprint (1967 November).
  - "Vietnam: Dead End in Asia,", 1967 October (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Mimeograph and printed copy inserted by Senator Vance Hartke in Congressional Record (1967 October 20).
  - "If We Had Permitted the Geneva Accords to Become Effective," Grass Roots Forum, 1967 December 30 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - "An Admiral Speaks on Vietnam: Civilization Depends on Co-existence and Cooperation," Churchman, 1968 March (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Message to Eugene McCarthy campaign headquarters, 1968 March (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - "The Gulf of Tonkin Incidents,", 1968 March (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Printed copy of correspondence with J. William Fulbright inserted by Fulbright in the Congressional Record (1968 March 27).
  - "An Honorable Peace," Grass Roots Forum, 1968 August 17 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Statement to Democratic Party National Convention Platform Committee, Washington, D.C., 1968 August 20 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Testimony on behalf of Friends Committee on National Legislation to U.S. Senate Armed Services Committee opposing Department of Defense budget requests, Washington, D.C., 1969 May (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - "Report of U.S. Study Team on Religious and Political Freedom in Vietnam,", 1969 June (Box-folder 6: 9)
    Collective report by True and other team members. Printed copy inserted in Congressional Record by Senator Abraham Ribicoff (1969 June 17).
  - "The Hoa Binh Study: An Inquiry into Political and Religious Freedom in Vietnam,", 1969 June (Box-folder 6: 10)
    Mimeograph. Individual report by True as member of U.S. Study Team on Religious and Political Freedom in Vietnam.
  - Christmas message, 1969 December (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Statement on Vietnam for Committee of Responsibility, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    Holograph.
  - Statement to court on behalf of John Braxton, draft resister, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1970 December 13 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    Typescript. Includes related letters and clippings.
  - "American Prisoners in Vietnam,", 1970 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - "Effect of the Vietnam War on National Security,", circa 1970 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - "On Surveillance of Civilians by the Military,", 1971 January 12 (Box-folder 6: 16)
    Statement by True issued as press release by Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace.
  - "National Security,", 1972 (Box-folder 6: 17)
    Typescript. Written for George McGovern campaign committee.
  - "A Brief for World Community," speech, World Citizens Assembly, San Francisco, California, 1975 July 22 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - "Dialogue with National Security,", 1975 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - "The Happy Kingdom,", 1976 September 30 (Box-folder 6: 20)
  - Autobiographical writings, circa 1978-1979 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Thirty-two autobiographical vignettes intended as parts of an uncompleted autobiography.
  - "Christmas Eve Off Death Island,", 1979 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    Typescript and printed copy in The Way It Was: As Told By Those Who Were There (collection of writings by members of a Palo Alto, California senior citizens writing group).
  - "A Definition of God,", undated (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - "SALT II,", undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - "The United Nations,", undated (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Letters to the editor
    - Re Japanese American internment (with Corinne True), San Carlos Enquirer, 1943 November 19 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - Re Vietnam War, Progressive, 1965 May (Box-folder 7: 7)
      Typescript, mimeograph, and printed copy.
    - General, 1961-1977 (Box-folder 7: 8)
      Typescripts and printed copies. Assorted letters to the editor, mainly re Vietnam War and other peace issues.
  - Poems, 1932-1978 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    Holographs and typescripts.
  - Speech notes, mainly re Vietnam War and other peace issues, 1966-1976 (Box-folder 7: 10-11)
  - Speech notes, mainly re Vietnam War and other peace issues (cont'd.), 1966-1976 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 8: 2)
    Notes and fragments.
- Correspondence, 1885-1987 (Boxes 8-10)
  Includes family correspondence and correspondence of Corinne True after her husband's death.
  - General, 1942-1986
    - 1942-1957 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - 1961-1966 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - 1967-1969 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - 1970-1978 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - 1980-1986 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Undated (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Family correspondence, 1885-1979 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Unanswered letters to high government officials re public policy issues, 1948-1977 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Abrams, Irwin, 1947-1954 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - Anderson, John Z. (Congressman), re Japanese American internment, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Arms of Friendship (person-to-person Soviet-American pen pal program), 1960-1962 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Belli, Melvin M., 1968 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Business Executives Move for Vietnam Peace, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Conyers, John, Jr. (Congressman), 1969 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Cousins, Norman (Saturday Review), 1975 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Davis, Rennie, 1968 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - Deakin, James (St. Louis Post-Dispatch), 1967 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Drinan, Robert F. (Congressman), 1970-1982 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Duncan, Donald W. (Ramparts; Support Our Soldiers), 1968-1969 (Box-folder 9: 15)
  - Fleming, D. F., 1966-1971 (Box-folder 9: 16)
  - Ford, William Wallace (General), 1967-1976 (Box-folder 9: 17)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1951-1967 (Box-folder 9: 18)
  - Fulbright, J. William (Senator), 1966-1974 (Box-folder 9: 19)
  - Goertzel, Victor, 1977 (Box-folder 9: 20)
  - Gore, Albert (Senator), 1970 (Box-folder 9: 21)
  - Gorman, Patrick E., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 22)
  - Greene, Felix, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9: 23)
  - Havrilla, Joseph and Lorraine, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 9: 24)
  - Heisler, Francis, re Tonkin Gulf incident, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 25)
  - Hester, Hugh B. (General), 1976 (Box-folder 9: 26)
  - Jarrell, Albert E. (Admiral), 1965 (Box-folder 9: 27)
  - Kahn, Albert E., 1973 (Box-folder 9: 28)
  - Keating, Edward M., 1967 (Box-folder 9: 29)
  - Kita, Hiromasa, 1965-1984 (Box-folder 9: 30)
  - La Rocque, Gene R. (Admiral; Center for Defense Information), 1972-1987 (Box-folder 9: 31)
  - Lord, Walter, re Battle of Midway, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 9: 32)
  - McDermid, Nancy, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - McGovern, George (Senator), 1972-1973 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1965 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Nixon, Richard M. (President), 1969-1971 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Overseas Vietnamese Buddhist Association, 1969 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Palo Alto Friends Meeting, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Pauling, Linus, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - Petersen, Gerald A., 1966-1976 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Ribicoff, Abraham (Senator), 1969 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Sabin, L. S. (Admiral), 1965-1968 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Shaw, Norman, mainly re U.S.S. Hammann, 1976-1982 (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - Smith, Sheldon D., 1971-1978 (Box-folder 10: 12)
  - Sombart, George and Mary, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 10: 13)
  - Spock, Benjamin, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - Triplett, Hall, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 15)
  - United States Department of Defense, re conscientious objectors, 1966 (Box-folder 10: 16)
  - United States Department of State, 1965 (Box-folder 10: 17)
  - United States Selective Service System (letters on behalf of individual conscientious objectors), 1967-1971 (Box-folder 10: 18)
  - Veterans for Peace, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 10: 19)
  - Warren, Earl (Governor), 1951 (Box-folder 10: 20)
  - Windchy, Eugene G., re Gulf of Tonkin incident, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 10: 21)
- Freedom of Information Act File, 1987-1990 (Boxes 10-11)
  Responses by U.S. government agencies to Freedom of Information Act requests by Corinne True with redacted photocopies of records provided.
  - General (Box-folder 10: 22)
  - United States Central Intelligence Agency, 1987 (Box-folder 10: 23)
  - United States Department of Defense, 1989 (Box-folder 10: 24)
  - United States Department of State, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 10: 25)
    Responses include photocopies of passport documents.
  - United States Department of the Air Force, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 10: 26)
    Responses include redacted photocopy of Defense Intelligence Agency report.
  - United States Department of the Army, 1990 (Box-folder 10: 27)
    Response includes redacted photocopy of intelligence report.
  - United States Department of the Navy, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    Responses include photocopies of Naval Academy records and redacted photocopies of intelligence reports.
  - United States Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 11: 2-4)
    Responses include redacted photocopies of intelligence reports.
  - United States National Security Agency, 1987 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - United States Postal Service, 1987 (Box-folder 11: 6)
- Subject File, 1943-1986 (Box 12)
  Printed matter and miscellany not directly relating to Arnold Ellsworth True.
  - Meteorology, 1943-1968 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    Speech, printed article, and clipping.
  - Peace, 1946-1983
    Much of this material relates to the Vietnam War and associated anti-war movement, but it also includes material on more general issues of peace.
    - Clippings, 1946-1983 (Box-folder 12: 2-4)
    - Printed articles, 1947-1978 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Newsletters and serial issues, 1963-1971 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Pamphlets, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - Leaflets and flyers, 1961-1974 (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - Resolutions, statements and circulars, 1959-1974 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - Congressional Record excerpts, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - D. F. Fleming printed articles, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - Art Hoppe newspaper columns (San Francisco Chronicle), 1965-1971 (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Stanford University press releases, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - South Vietnamese publications, 1969 (Box-folder 13: 6)
    Leaflets, clippings and serial issues collected by True during his visit to South Vietnam with the U.S. Study Team on Religious and Political Freedom in Vietnam.
  - Other foreign publications, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    Soviet and South Korean newspaper issues.
  - United States Navy, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    Printed matter and miscellany. Includes material on Battle of Midway and on U.S.S. Rizal, a ship on which True served.
  - Miscellany, 1953-1981 (Box-folder 13: 9)
    Printed matter.
- Oversize File, 1918-1951 (Box 14)
  Scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbook of Nannie True, mother of Arnold Ellsworth True, including poems, letters and clippings, 1918-1951 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook re World War II service of Arnold Ellsworth True on U.S.S. Hammann, including letters, clippings and photographs, 1942-1943 (Box 14)
- Audiovisual File, circa 1886-1979 (Boxes 14-16)
  Photographs, drawing, watercolor, and sound recordings.
  - Album of family and naval service photographs, circa 1886-1954 (Box 14)
  - Photographs of family and naval service scenes, 1930s-1970s (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - Photocopies of photographs, mainly of family scenes, 1900s-1970s (Box-folder 15: 2)
  - Drawing of Arnold Ellsworth True, undated (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - Watercolor of Tanforan Internment Camp, California, painted by Hikari Inouye, 1942 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - Two sound discs, circa 1970 (Box 16)